<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pgen</journal-id><journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name> <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030062</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">07-PLGE-RA-0083R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="sici">plge-03-04-11</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17447844</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Developmental Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Dmrt7</subject><subject>DM domain</subject><subject>XY body</subject><subject>Meiosis</subject><subject>Gametogenesis</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A Mammal-Specific <italic>Doublesex</italic> Homolog Associates with Male Sex Chromatin and Is Required for Male Meiosis</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">A DM Domain Protein in Male Meiosis</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Shinseog</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Namekawa</surname><given-names>Satoshi H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Niswander</surname><given-names>Lisa M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>Jeremy O</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Jeannie T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bardwell</surname><given-names>Vivian J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zarkower</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label> Department of Genetics, Cell Biology, and Development, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minnesota, United States of America
			</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> Biochemistry, Molecular Biology, and Biophysics Graduate Program, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minnesota, United States of America
			</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label> Department of Molecular Biology, Massachusetts General Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America
			</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label> Department of Genetics, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America
			</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label> Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America
			</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label> Department of Biology, Middlebury College, Middlebury, Vermont, United States of America
			</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Schimenti</surname><given-names>John C</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Cornell University, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>zarko001&#x00040;umn.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>4</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epreprint"><day>7</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e62</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2007</year></date></history><copyright-statement><bold>Copyright:</bold> &#x000a9; 2007 Kim et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><!--<related-article related-article-type="preprint" xlink:title="Research Article" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pgen.0030062.eor" xlink:type="simple" >A mammal-specific Doublesex homolog associates with male sex chromatin and is required for male meiosis</related-article>--><abstract><p>Gametogenesis is a sexually dimorphic process requiring profound differences in germ cell differentiation between the sexes. In mammals, the presence of heteromorphic sex chromosomes in males creates additional sex-specific challenges, including incomplete X and Y pairing during meiotic prophase. This triggers formation of a heterochromatin domain, the XY body. The XY body disassembles after prophase, but specialized sex chromatin persists, with further modification, through meiosis. Here, we investigate the function of DMRT7, a mammal-specific protein related to the invertebrate sexual regulators Doublesex and MAB-3. We find that DMRT7 preferentially localizes to the XY body in the pachytene stage of meiotic prophase and is required for male meiosis. In <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutants, meiotic pairing and recombination appear normal, and a transcriptionally silenced XY body with appropriate chromatin marks is formed, but most germ cells undergo apoptosis during pachynema. A minority of mutant cells can progress to diplonema, but many of these escaping cells have abnormal sex chromatin lacking histone H3K9 di- and trimethylation and heterochromatin protein 1&#x003b2; accumulation, modifications that normally occur between pachynema and diplonema. Based on the localization of DMRT7 to the XY body and the sex chromatin defects observed in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutants, we conclude that DMRT7 plays a role in the sex chromatin transformation that occurs between pachynema and diplonema. We suggest that DMRT7 may help control the transition from meiotic sex chromosome inactivation to postmeiotic sex chromatin in males. In addition, because it is found in all branches of mammals, but not in other vertebrates, <italic>Dmrt7</italic> may shed light on evolution of meiosis and of sex chromatin.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title><sec id="st1"><title/><p>Genes related to the sexual regulator <italic>Doublesex</italic> of <italic>Drosophila</italic> have been found to control sexual development in a wide variety of animals, ranging from roundworms to mammals. In this paper, we investigate the function of the <italic>Dmrt7</italic> gene, one of seven related genes in the mouse. Female mammals are XX and males are XY, a chromosomal difference that presents specific challenges during the meiotic phase of male germ cell development. Some of these are thought to be overcome by incorporating the X and Y chromosomes into a specialized structure called the XY body. We find that DMRT7 protein is present in germ cells, localizes to the male XY body during meiosis, and is essential for male but not female fertility. The XY body normally is altered by recruitment of additional proteins and by specific modifications to histone proteins between the pachytene and diplotene stages of meiosis, but modification of the &#x0201c;sex chromatin&#x0201d; in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant cells is abnormal during this period. Because <italic>Dmrt7</italic> is found in all branches of mammals, but not in other vertebrates, these results may indicate some commonality in regulation of sex chromatin among the mammals.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>citation</meta-name><meta-value>Kim S, Namekawa SH, Niswander LM, Ward JO, Lee JT, et al. (2007) A mammal-specific <italic>Doublesex</italic> homolog associates with male sex chromatin and is required for male meiosis. PLoS Genet 3(4): e62. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pgen.0030062">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030062</ext-link></meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Sexual differentiation generates anatomical, physiological, and behavioral dimorphisms that are essential for sexual reproduction. Many of these dimorphisms affect somatic cells, but the sexual dimorphisms that most directly mediate sexual reproduction are those of the gametes themselves. Gametes differ between the sexes in size and morphology, sometimes dramatically so, reflecting their very different roles in zygote formation. Indeed, the morphology of the gametes is what defines sex: females are the sex that produces the larger gametes and males produce the smaller ones.</p><p>Mammalian meiosis is regulated sex-specifically starting in embryogenesis and continuing through much of adult life (reviewed in &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b001">1</xref>&#x0005d;). For example, the timing and synchrony of meiosis are very different in the two sexes. In females, germ cells synchronously initiate meiosis in the embryo and arrest during meiotic prophase I. After puberty, oocytes are selectively recruited for ovulation, when they proceed to metaphase II and then complete meiosis after fertilization occurs &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b002">2</xref>&#x0005d;. In contrast, male meiosis occurs entirely postnatally, without the arrest periods found in females. In females, each meiosis can produce a single haploid oocyte (and two extruded polar bodies), whereas each male meiosis can produce four haploid spermatocytes.</p><p>Other meiotic processes, such as recombination and chromosome pairing (synapsis), occur in both sexes but operate somewhat differently. For example, there is a higher failure rate for meiosis in females, with human oocyte aneuploidy rates up to 25&#x00025; versus about 2&#x00025; in human sperm &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b003">3</xref>&#x0005d;, and this may indicate that the checkpoints controlling and monitoring the events of meiotic progression in males are more stringent. Consistent with this idea, genetic analysis of a number of meiotic regulatory genes in the mouse has demonstrated a much stronger requirement in males than in females &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b001">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b004">4</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>The existence of heteromorphic sex chromosomes, such as the XX/XY system of mammals, creates sex-specific challenges. One is the need for mechanisms to balance expression of sex-linked genes between the sexes, which in mammals is accomplished by X chromosome inactivation in females &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b005">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b006">6</xref>&#x0005d;. In male germ cells there is another sex-specific consideration during meiosis. In prophase I, when the homologous chromosomes synapse and homologous recombination occurs, X and Y chromosome pairing is limited to a region termed the pseudoautosomal region, leaving large portions of each chromosome unpaired. In eutherian and marsupial mammals, these unpaired chromosome regions are associated with a specialized chromatin domain termed the XY body or sex body. The function of the XY body is uncertain &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b007">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b011">11</xref>&#x0005d;, but there is evidence that it is essential for male meiotic progression &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b012">12</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>Several proteins are reported to localize to the XY body, including BRCA1, ATR, the histone variant H3.3, and modified histones such as ubiquitinated H2A (Ub-H2A) and phosphorylated H2AX (&#x003b3;H2AX) &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b012">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b015">15</xref>&#x0005d;. In the XY body, the sex chromosomes are transcriptionally silenced in a process termed meiotic sex chromosome inactivation (MSCI). The XY body disappears after pachynema; however, many sex-linked genes remain transcriptionally silent into spermiogenesis &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b016">16</xref>&#x0005d;. This maintenance of silencing is associated with a distinct set of chromatin marks that define a sex chromatin domain termed postmeiotic sex chromatin (PMSC) &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b016">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b017">17</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>Regulators of sexual differentiation have been identified in a number of organisms, but in contrast to many other developmental processes, such as axial patterning or development of many body parts, the molecular mechanisms that regulate sexual differentiation are highly variable between phyla. A notable exception involves genes related to <italic>doublesex (dsx)</italic> of <italic>Drosophila,</italic> which share a Doublesex/MAB-3 DNA-binding motif called the DM domain &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b019">19</xref>&#x0005d;. DM domain&#x02013;encoding genes have been shown to regulate various aspects of sexual differentiation in insects, nematodes, and mammals &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b020">20</xref>&#x0005d;. The <italic>mab-3</italic> gene of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Caenorhabditis elegans</named-content> has been shown to function analogously to DSX in several respects and can be functionally replaced by the male isoform of DSX, suggesting that the similarity in the sequence of these genes may stem from conservation of an ancestral DM domain sexual regulator &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b021">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b022">22</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>Vertebrates also have DM domain genes, and analysis to date, although limited, has shown that these genes also control sexual differentiation. Mammals have seven DM domain genes (<italic>Dmrt</italic> genes), several of which exhibit sexually dimorphic mRNA expression &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b023">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b024">24</xref>&#x0005d;. The best studied of these genes, <italic>Dmrt1,</italic> is expressed in the differentiating male genital ridges and adult testis of mammals, birds, fish, and reptiles, and a recently duplicated <italic>Dmrt1</italic> gene functions as the Y-linked testis-determining gene in the Medaka fish &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b025">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b029">29</xref>&#x0005d;. Human <italic>DMRT1</italic> maps to an autosomal locus, which, when hemizygous, is associated with defective testicular development and consequent XY feminization &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b030">30</xref>&#x0005d;. Similarly, mice homozygous for a null mutation in <italic>Dmrt1</italic> have severe defects in testis differentiation involving both germ cells and Sertoli cells &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b031">31</xref>&#x0005d;. Female mice mutant in <italic>Dmrt4</italic> have polyovular follicles, indicating that this gene also plays a role in gonadal development &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b032">32</xref>&#x0005d;. It appears from these studies that the involvement of DM domain genes in sexual differentiation is ancient and conserved. However, vertebrate <italic>Dmrt</italic> gene function is not limited to sexual differentiation: <italic>Dmrt2</italic> is required in both sexes for segmentation in mice and fish &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b033">33</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b035">35</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>Here, we have investigated the expression and function of the <italic>Dmrt7</italic> gene in the mouse<italic>. Dmrt7</italic> is expressed only in the gonad, and, unlike the other <italic>Dmrt</italic> genes, appears to be present exclusively in mammals and not in nonmammalian vertebrates &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b023">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b036">36</xref>&#x0005d;. We find that DMRT7 protein is expressed only in germ cells and is selectively localized to the XY body of male pachytene germ cells. To test its function, we generated a conditional null mutation of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> in the mouse. We find that <italic>Dmrt7</italic> is required in males for progression beyond the pachytene stage of meiotic prophase but is not required in females. In rare mutant cells that survive to diplonema, we observed sex chromatin abnormalities. Based on these observations, we suggest that <italic>Dmrt7</italic> plays a critical role in a male-specific chromatin transition between pachynema and diplonema during meiotic prophase.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Expression of DMRT7 Proteins in Testis</title><p>Our previous mRNA expression analysis suggested a possible meiotic function for <italic>Dmrt7,</italic> based on the expression of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mRNA in the fetal gonads of the two sexes &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b023">23</xref>&#x0005d;. In the fetal ovary, <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mRNA was detected primarily from E13.5 to E15.5, the time during which meiosis progresses from pre-meiotic replication to the pachytene stage &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b004">4</xref>&#x0005d;, whereas <italic>Dmrt7</italic> expression in the non-meiotic fetal testis was very low. Because this earlier work did not examine adult <italic>Dmrt7</italic> expression, we first performed reverse transcriptase (RT)-PCR on mRNA from ten adult organs and detected strong <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mRNA expression in the testis and a trace of expression in heart, but not in any other tissue tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g001">Figure 1</xref>A). We examined the timing of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mRNA expression during postnatal testis development and detected strong expression beginning at 2 wk, which roughly coincides with the onset of the pachytene stage during the first synchronous wave of spermatogenesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g001">Figure 1</xref>B) &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b037">37</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><fig id="pgen-0030062-g001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Expression of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mRNA and Protein</title><p>(A) RT-PCR analysis of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mRNA from ten organs of adult mouse. cDNA from each organ was amplified with primers specific for <italic>Dmrt7</italic> (top row) and &#x003b2;-<italic>actin</italic> (bottom row).</p><p>(B) <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mRNA expression during the first round of spermatogenesis. cDNAs obtained from testis at the indicated days after birth were amplified as in (A).</p><p>(C) DMRT7 protein expression. Immunofluorescence of testis sections from 6-wk-old male stained with antibody to DMRT7 (green) and DAPI (blue).</p><p>(D) DMRT7 subcellular localization to XY body. Testis sections from 6-wk-old male stained with antibodies to DMRT7 (red) and SUMO-1 (green). SUMO-1 is localized to the XY body. Right-most panel shows merge of other two panels. Inserts show higher magnification of pachytene spermatocytes with XY bodies.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030062.g001"/></fig><p>To investigate DMRT7 protein expression, we generated an antibody against the C-terminal portion of the protein. The antibody was raised against a unique region lacking the DM domain in order to avoid cross-reaction with other DM domain proteins. Immunofluorescent staining with purified DMRT7 antisera showed that DMRT7 protein is expressed predominantly in mid- to late-pachytene spermatocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g001">Figure 1</xref>C), as well as in sperm, and is not detectable in other germ cell types including spermatogonia and round spermatids. We did not detect DMRT7 protein in somatic cells such as Sertoli cells, peritubular myoid cells, or Leydig cells. To more precisely determine the pachytene stages of DMRT7 expression, we double-stained with an antibody to GATA1, which is expressed in Sertoli cells from stages VII to IX &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b038">38</xref>&#x0005d;. This confirmed that DMRT7 is expressed in mid- to late-pachytene spermatocytes, starting slightly earlier than stage VII and extending through stage IX (unpublished data).</p><p>Within pachytene spermatocytes, DMRT7 is concentrated in the XY body, or sex body, a densely staining chromatin domain that harbors the sex chromosomes. These undergo transcriptional inactivation and heterochromatinization as a result of their incomplete pairing during prophase of mammalian male meiosis &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b017">17</xref>&#x0005d;. To verify DMRT7 protein expression in the XY body, we double-stained mouse testis sections for DMRT7 and small ubiquitin-related modifier 1 (SUMO-1), which is concentrated in the XY body during pachynema &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b039">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b040">40</xref>&#x0005d;. DMRT7 and SUMO-1 were colocalized, confirming that DMRT7 protein is preferentially localized to the XY body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g001">Figure 1</xref>D). We also confirmed XY body localization of DMRT7 by double staining for other markers including Ub-H2A and &#x003b3;H2AX (unpublished data). DMRT7 is not preferentially localized to the XY body at all stages but instead is dynamic. Based on epithelial staging, it appears that DMRT7 localizes to the XY body from mid- to late-pachynema, becomes diffusely distributed in late-pachynema, and disappears in diplonema (unpublished data). This localization was confirmed by staining of meiotic spreads (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030062-sg001">Figure S1</xref>). DMRT7 also is specifically localized in sperm, with antibody staining mainly in the perinuclear ring of the sperm head manchette. This staining coincided with the epithelial stages in which DMRT7 localizes to the XY body in spermatocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g001">Figure 1</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g001">1</xref>D).</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Targeted Deletion of <italic>Dmrt7</italic></title><p>To establish the functional requirement for <italic>Dmrt7,</italic> we generated <italic>Dmrt7</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice by targeted disruption in embryonic stem (ES) cells using a strategy diagrammed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030062-sg002">Figure S2</xref>A. The <italic>Dmrt7</italic> gene has nine exons with the DM domain encoded by the second and third exons. Because the DM domain is essential for function of other genes, including <italic>mab-3, mab-23,</italic> and <italic>dsx</italic> &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b018">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b019">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b041">41</xref>&#x0005d;, we generated a conditionally targeted &#x0201c;floxed&#x0201d; allele in which the DM domain&#x02013;containing exons of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> are flanked by recognition sites for the Cre recombinase (<italic>loxP</italic> sites). The targeting vector also contained a neomycin resistance cassette <italic>(neo)</italic> flanked by Flpe recognition sites. The removal of these sequences by Cre-mediated recombination eliminates the DM domain and the translational start site, thus generating a putative null allele. We identified three homologously targeted ES cell clones by Southern blotting (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030062-sg002">Figure S2</xref>B) and injected cells from two clones into C57BL/6 blastocysts. Chimeric animals from both cell lines transmitted the targeted allele through the germ line. Targeted animals were bred to &#x003b2;<italic>-actin Cre</italic> mice to delete the DM domain&#x02013;encoding exons, generating the <italic>Dmrt7<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic> allele, or to <italic>Flpe</italic> transgenic mice to delete the <italic>neo</italic> cassette, generating the <italic>Dmrt7<sup>flox</sup></italic> allele. <italic>Dmrt7<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice were interbred to generate <italic>Dmrt7<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice. To confirm the lack of functional DMRT7 protein in <italic>Dmrt7<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>testes, we stained meiotic spreads from <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030062-sg001">Figure S1</xref>) and sections from mutant testes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030062-sg002">Figure S2</xref>C) and carried out western blot analysis (unpublished data). In each case, we detected no DMRT7 protein in the mutant testes.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><italic>Dmrt7</italic> Is Required for Male but Not Female Gametogenesis</title><p>Breeding of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> heterozygotes produced homozygous mutant progeny of both sexes at the expected frequency (63/264; 23&#x00025;). Male and female homozygous mutants were viable, grew to adulthood normally, and exhibited normal sexual behavior. Female homozygotes were fertile, produced litters of normal size, and had no obvious ovarian abnormalities as judged by histological analysis (unpublished data). In contrast, <italic>Dmrt7</italic> homozygous mutant males were completely infertile and had testes about one-third the weight of those of heterozygous or wild-type adult littermates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g002">Figure 2</xref>). To determine when defective testis development begins in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutants, we compared the testes of wild-type and mutant littermates during the first wave of spermatogenesis. Prior to postnatal day 14 (P14), mutant testes appeared histologically normal and the testis weights were similar to those of heterozygous and wild-type littermates, indicating that spermatogonia and early meiotic germ cells form normally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g002">Figure 2</xref>B; unpublished data). Thereafter, the testes of the <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant mice ceased to grow and the weight difference was significant. Microscopic examination of P21 and P42 <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant testes revealed that germ cells arrest in pachynema, and later stages of germ cells are largely missing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g002">Figure 2</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g002">2</xref>D). <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant mice are deficient in postmeiotic spermatids and lack epididymal spermatozoa, although a few cells develop to the round spermatid stage. These meiotic defects are in agreement with a recent preliminary analysis of another <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutation &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b042">42</xref>&#x0005d;. While some <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant tubules are highly vacuolated and contain primarily Sertoli cells and spermatogonia, others have abundant primary spermatocytes. In addition, some tubules contain multinucleated cells and cells with darkly stained nuclei that are typical of apoptotic cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g002">Figure 2</xref>D).</p><fig id="pgen-0030062-g002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Reduced Testis Size and Germ Cell Apoptosis in Mice with Targeted Deletion in <italic>Dmrt7</italic></title><p>(A) Testes from a 6-wk-old wild-type (&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;) mouse and a homozygous (&#x02212;/&#x02212;) <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant littermate.</p><p>(B&#x02013;D) Sections of testes from 14-d-old (B), 21-d-old (C), and 42-d-old mice (D) stained with hematoxylin and eosin. Wild-type is in left column and mutant in right. No significant difference is observed at 14 d (B), but by 21 d some tubules are lacking abundant spermatocytes (C, asterisk) or cells with typical apoptotic morphology are present (open arrowhead, C and D). Mutant tubules contain multinucleate cells (closed arrowhead, D).</p><p>(E and F) TUNEL labeling of <italic>Dmrt7</italic>-deficient mouse testes. Testes from wild-type and homozygous mutant littermates were analyzed by TUNEL labeling to detect apoptotic cells. Testis sections from 21-d-old (E) and 6-wk-old mice (F). Apoptotic cells (brown) are much more abundant in seminiferous tubules of homozygous <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant mice relative to wild-type. Bars in (B&#x02013;F) represent 100 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030062.g002"/></fig><p>Since <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant testes lack most post-pachytene cells, we used TUNEL analysis to test whether the missing cells are eliminated by apoptosis. At 3 wk, <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant testes contain significantly more apoptotic cells than those of wild-type controls. The percentage of tubule sections with five or more apoptotic nuclei was about three times higher in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutants compared with wild-type (20&#x00025; versus 7&#x00025;; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g002">Figure 2</xref>E). A similar elevation of apoptosis was apparent in mutant testes at 7 wk (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g002">Figure 2</xref>F). In mutants, many apoptotic cells were in the middle of the tubules, whereas the apoptotic cells in wild-type occur mainly near the seminiferous tubule periphery. The numbers of Sertoli cells were not significantly different between wild-type and mutant testes, and we observed no difference in somatic cell apoptosis in mutants (unpublished data). From these results, we conclude that loss of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> causes a block in meiotic progression, mainly in pachynema, leading to the elimination, by apoptosis, of the arrested cells.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Pachytene Arrest of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> Mutant Germ Cells</title><p>To better define the spermatogenic stage at which <italic>Dmrt7<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> male germ cells arrest and die, we used antibodies against several stage-specific germ cell markers. TRA98 is expressed in PGCs and spermatogonia &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b043">43</xref>&#x0005d;. In the wild-type adult testis, strongly staining TRA98-positive cells form a layer one cell deep; however, in the mutant TRA98, strongly positive cells were abnormally organized, and some tubules had a layer several cells deep (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g003">Figure 3</xref>A). The BC7 antibody recognizes spermatocytes in the leptotene to early-pachytene stages &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b044">44</xref>&#x0005d;. <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant testes had BC7-positive cells in approximately normal numbers, but again abnormally organized, with many positive cells in the center rather than the periphery of the tubules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g003">Figure 3</xref>B). The TRA369 antibody recognizes a calmegin protein expressed in pachytene spermatocytes through elongated spermatids &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b045">45</xref>&#x0005d;. In contrast to the earlier stages, far fewer TRA369-positive cells were present in mutant testes relative to wild-type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g003">Figure 3</xref>C). We also quantitated the number of cells at each meiotic stage using spermatocyte spreads, assaying chromosome-pairing status by staining for SYCP3, a component of the synaptonemal complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g004">Figure 4</xref>). We found that <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutants accumulate pachytene cells but have greatly reduced numbers of cells in late-pachynema and beyond. Together, these results confirm that the meiotic arrest in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutants occurs primarily during pachynema and results in efficient elimination of arrested cells.</p><fig id="pgen-0030062-g003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Prophase I Arrest of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> Mutant Germ Cells</title><p>Testis sections from 6-wk-old wild-type (&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;) and <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant (&#x02212;/&#x02212;) littermates stained with stage-specific antibodies specific to spermatogenic cells.</p><p>(A) TRA98 antibody strongly stains spermatogonia, which are present in wild-type and mutant.</p><p>(B) BC7 antibody stains spermatocytes, which are present in wild-type and mutant.</p><p>(C) TRA369 antibody stains pachytene and later germ cells, which are severely deficient in the mutant testis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030062.g003"/></fig><fig id="pgen-0030062-g004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Profile of Meiotic Arrest in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> Mutant Testis</title><p>Graph of distribution of meiotic stages of germ cells from heterozygous (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 1,970) and homozygous mutant (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 2,084) P26 testes, spread and stained for the synaptonemal complex protein SYCP3 to permit precise staging, which was performed as described &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b064">64</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b065">65</xref>&#x0005d;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030062.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Normal Meiotic Prophase in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> Mutant Germ Cells</title><p>Defects in chromosome pairing, synapsis, or recombination can trigger pachytene arrest and apoptosis &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b046">46</xref>&#x0005d;. We therefore examined these events in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant testes. To assess homolog synapsis, we used antibodies to SYCP1, a synaptonemal complex transverse element component, and SYCP3, a component of the axial element, which remains on the desynapsed axes during diplonema &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b047">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b048">48</xref>&#x0005d;. Formation of synaptonemal complexes in the mutant was indistinguishable from that in wild-type, as indicated by the proper accumulation of SYCP1 (unpublished data) and SYCP3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g005">Figure 5</xref>A). Likewise, the <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant zygotene spermatocytes showed normal accumulation of the early recombination repair marker RAD51, suggesting that early meiotic recombination is not significantly affected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g005">Figure 5</xref>B). <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant spermatocytes exhibited the expected decline in the presence of RAD51 foci associated with the autosomal synaptonemal complexes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g005">Figure 5</xref>B; unpublished data) &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b049">49</xref>&#x0005d;. The few surviving cells that progressed beyond pachynema also underwent apparently normal desynapsis during diplonema (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g005">Figure 5</xref>A). From these results, we conclude that chromosomal pairing, synapsis, recombination, and desynapsis during prophase I in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant males are grossly normal.</p><fig id="pgen-0030062-g005" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Normal Synapsis and Recombination in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> Mutant Germ Cells</title><p>(A) Testicular cells from <italic>Dmrt7</italic> heterozygous (&#x0002b;/&#x02212;) or homozygous (&#x02212;/&#x02212;) mutant mice were spread and stained with antibody to SYCP3 (red). The developmental stages of meiotic prophase based on SYCP3 organization are indicated in each panel. By pachynema, all autosomes are fully synapsed, and the XY bivalent is synapsed only at the pseudoautosomal region in both wild-type and mutant cells.</p><p>(B) Testicular cells in zygonema and pachynema spread and stained with antibodies to RAD51 (green) and SYCP3 (red). Size and distribution of RAD51 foci are similar between wild-type and mutant spermatocytes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030062.g005"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Abnormal Cellular Organization and the Role of Sertoli Cells</title><p>Sertoli cells interact with germ cells during spermatogenesis and the interaction is critical for germ cell maturation &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b050">50</xref>&#x0005d;. Although we did not detect DMRT7 expression in Sertoli cells by antibody staining, we nevertheless considered the possibility that Sertoli cell defects might contribute to the male-specific germ line failure of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutants. To characterize Sertoli cell differentiation, we examined expression of the Sertoli cell markers GATA4 (a marker of immature postnatal Sertoli cells) and GATA1 (a mature Sertoli cell marker). The levels of these proteins appeared normal relative to wild-type at P14 and P42 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g006">Figure 6</xref>A&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g006">6</xref>C), as did the androgen receptor (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030062-sg003">Figure S3</xref>; unpublished data). However, the organization of Sertoli cells in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant testes was abnormal: in some tubules GATA1-positive Sertoli cell nuclei were displaced from their usual close apposition with the basement membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g006">Figure 6</xref>C). In such tubules, nuclei of pre-meiotic germ cells and spermatocytes were packed close to the basal membrane and few germ cells were found in the adlumenal region.</p><fig id="pgen-0030062-g006" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Abnormal Sertoli Cell Organization in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> Mutant Testes</title><p>(A) Testes from P14 wild-type and <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant mice were sectioned and stained with antibody to GATA4.</p><p>(B) P14 testis sections stained with antibody to GATA1. At P14, GATA4 and GATA1 levels are similar in wild-type and mutant Sertoli cell.</p><p>(C) Wild-type and mutant testis sections double-stained with antibody to GATA1 (red) and DAPI (blue). Most Sertoli cell nuclei were adjacent to the basal membrane in wild-type, but mutant Sertoli cells were displaced in some tubules (arrowhead). White dotted line indicates position of basal membranes.</p><p>(D) Testis sections from 10-wk-old wild-type and Sertoli cell-specific <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant <italic>(SC-Dmrt7KO)</italic> mice stained with hematoxylin and eosin. Spermatogenesis and spermiogenesis are normal in <italic>SC-Dmrt7KO</italic> testis.</p><p>(E) Testis sections from 10-wk-old wild-type and <italic>SC-Dmrt7KO</italic> mice stained with antibodies to GATA1 (red) and smooth muscle actin (to outline seminiferous tubules; green). Sertoli cell nuclei are positioned normally near the basal membrane in <italic>SC-Dmrt7KO</italic> mice.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030062.g006"/></fig><p>The aberrant Sertoli cell organization in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant testes raised the possibility that the germ cell phenotype might indirectly result from defects in Sertoli cell function. To test this possibility, we deleted <italic>Dmrt7</italic> just in the Sertoli cell lineage by crossing mice carrying the floxed <italic>Dmrt7</italic> allele with <italic>Dhh-Cre</italic> transgenic mice &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b051">51</xref>&#x0005d;. The <italic>Desert hedgehog (Dhh)</italic> promoter is active starting at about E12.5 in pre-Sertoli cells but not in germ cells, allowing deletion of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> in Sertoli cells well before any likely requirement for its function &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b052">52</xref>&#x0005d;. Testicular size in Sertoli-targeted <italic>(SC-Dmrt7KO)</italic> animals was slightly reduced from that of wild-type, but histological analysis revealed no obvious difference between wild-type and <italic>SC-Dmrt7KO</italic> testes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g006">Figure 6</xref>D). Spermatogenesis appeared normal, mature sperm were present, and <italic>SC-Dmrt7KO</italic> mice were fertile. In addition, GATA1 staining showed that Sertoli cell nuclei were located adjacent to the basement membrane as in wild-type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g006">Figure 6</xref>E). These results suggest the germ cell defects of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutants are not caused by lack of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> in Sertoli cells. Rather, the abnormal organization of Sertoli cells appears to result from lack of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> in the germ line.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>XY Bodies Form Normally in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> Mutant Cells</title><p>The data presented so far indicate that <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant germ cells undergo apparently normal early meiosis and then arrest during pachynema due to a strict requirement for <italic>Dmrt7</italic> in the germ line. To better understand the basis of the meiotic arrest, we more closely examined meiotic germ cells in the mutant. We focused on the XY body, which is thought to be essential for meiotic progression and is the site of preferential DMRT7 localization. Condensation of the X and Y chromosomes begins in late-zygotene cells, and, by mid-pachynema (when homologous chromosome pairs are fully aligned) the sex chromatin forms a microscopically visible spherical structure near the nuclear periphery &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b053">53</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>We first asked whether DMRT7 is required for XY body formation by evaluating several characteristic XY body chromatin features. First, we tested &#x003b3;H2AX expression by immunofluorescent staining. H2AX is a variant of H2A that is crucial for XY body formation and MSCI &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b012">12</xref>&#x0005d;. &#x003b3;H2AX localized normally to the XY body of DMRT7 mutant cells in meiotic spreads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g007">Figure 7</xref>A), and many &#x003b3;H2AX-positive puncta were present in germ cells of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant testes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g007">Figure 7</xref>B). Next, we examined SUMO-1 localization in the mutant testis. SUMO-1 expression normally increases in the XY body of early- to mid-pachytene spermatocytes at the time of sex chromosome condensation. Prior to the completion of the first meiotic division, SUMO-1 disappears from the XY body as the X and Y chromosomes desynapse &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b040">40</xref>&#x0005d;. Punctate SUMO-1 localization was present in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant germ cells, again consistent with formation of a correctly marked XY body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g007">Figure 7</xref>C). However, some tubules in mutants had multiple layers of cells with SUMO-1-condensed spots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g007">Figure 7</xref>C), rather than the normal single layer of cells. This accumulation of XY body&#x02013;containing cells also was apparent with &#x003b3;H2AX staining and is consistent with a developmental arrest of mutant cells in mid- to late-pachytene. We also examined Ub-H2A localization in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant testes. In early-pachytene, Ub-H2A is concentrated in the XY body; by mid-pachytene Ub-H2A is observed throughout the entire nucleus, but it again becomes limited to the XY body in late-pachytene spermatocytes &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b013">13</xref>&#x0005d;. Analysis of nuclear spreads revealed that Ub-H2A localizes normally to the XY body in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030062-sg004">Figure S4</xref>). Collectively, these results indicate that <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant germ cells can establish an XY body with at least some of the normal chromatin marks.</p><fig id="pgen-0030062-g007" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>XY Body Forms Normally during Pachynema in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> Mutant Mice</title><p>(A) Testicular cells spread and stained with antibodies to &#x003b3;H2AX (red) and SYCP3 (green). In pachytene cells, &#x003b3;H2AX is concentrated in the XY body both in wild-type and <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant.</p><p>(B) Testes from 6-wk-old mice sectioned and stained with antibody to &#x003b3;H2AX (red).</p><p>(C) Testes from 6-wk-old mice sectioned and stained with antibody to SUMO-1 (green). Abundant pachytene cells with XY bodies are present in wild-type and mutant testes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030062.g007"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Abnormal Sex Chromatin in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> Mutant Germ Cells</title><p>Although the XY body can form during pachynema in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutants, we considered the possibility that transcriptional silencing might not be properly established. This would be consistent with the <italic>Dmrt7</italic> phenotype: pachytene cells that escape from MSCI normally are eliminated prior to late-pachytene &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b017">17</xref>&#x0005d;. Recently, MSCI has been shown to continue into meiosis II and spermiogenesis, apparently mediated by a distinct chromatin compartment termed postmeiotic sex chromatin (PMSC) that is established starting in diplonema &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b016">16</xref>&#x0005d;. We therefore asked whether the pachytene germ cell death in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutants is associated with a failure either to initiate or to maintain sex chromosome inactivation.</p><p>First, we examined the mid-pachytene XY body. To examine XY transcriptional status, we carried out Cot-1 RNA fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) to detect nascent RNA polymerase II transcription, combined with DAPI staining to locate the XY body on spreads of seminiferous tubules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g008">Figure 8</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g008">8</xref>B). In <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutants, the XY body was formed and excluded Cot-1 hybridization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g008">Figure 8</xref>B), indicating that transcriptional silencing is established normally in mutant pachytene cells. We also examined expression of the Y-linked gene <italic>Rbmy,</italic> which normally is inactivated during pachytene and reactivated after secondary meiosis begins &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b054">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b055">55</xref>&#x0005d;. <italic>Rbmy</italic> was inactivated normally in pachytene cells of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutants, based on immunofluorescent staining with an anti-RBMY antibody (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030062-sg005">Figure S5</xref>). We also examined heterochromatin protein 1 beta (HP1&#x003b2;), which normally localizes to the X centromere at mid-pachynema and then spreads through the XY body as it internalizes during diplonema &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b056">56</xref>&#x0005d;. We found that HP1&#x003b2; localization is normal in DMRT7 mutant cells in mid-pachynema (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g008">Figure 8</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g008">8</xref>D). These results suggest that XY body formation and initiation of MSCI both occur normally in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant germ cells.</p><fig id="pgen-0030062-g008" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Chromatin Abnormalities in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> Mutant Diplotene Germ Cells</title><p>(A and B) MSCI occurs normally in mid-pachytene spermatocyte of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant. Arrows indicate XY body in all panels. Cot-1 RNA FISH (red) reveals normal silencing of sex chromosome transcription in XY body. This is consistent with wild-type mid-pachynema as described previously &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b016">16</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>(C and D) HP1&#x003b2; localization in mid-pachytene spermatocytes. HP1&#x003b2; localizes to X chromosome centromere (arrowhead) in wild-type (C) and mutant (D).</p><p>(E and F) Cot-1 hybridization in diplotene. Presumptive XY body, based on DAPI and &#x003b3;H2AX localization, is indicated by arrow in (F).</p><p>(G and H) HP1&#x003b2; in diplotene. Wild-type cell (E) has HP1&#x003b2; throughout XY body, whereas mutant cell (H) only has localization to X chromosome centromere (arrowhead).</p><p>(I and J) H3-2meK9 localization in diplotene cells. Mutant cell (J) lacks strong concentration of this mark to the XY body seen in wild-type (I).</p><p>(K and L) H3-3meK9 localization in diplotene cells. Mutant cell (L) has no localization of this mark to the XY body. &#x003b3;H2AX localizes to autosomes in mutant cell, possibly indicating onset of apoptosis.</p><p>(M) Example of mutant diplotene cell with normal HP1&#x003b2; accumulation to the XY body.</p><p>All images except those in (M) are single Z sections.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030062.g008"/></fig><p>We next considered the possibility that sex chromatin is established normally but is not properly modified as cells exit pachynema and begin to form PMSC. Although most <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant cells are eliminated by apoptosis prior to diplonema, we were able to examine epigenetic markers of PMSC in rare <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant spermatocytes that escaped pachytene arrest and progressed into diplonema. First, we examined nascent transcription by Cot-1 hybridization. Although heterochromatic regions generally showed lower Cot-1 signal than euchromatic regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g008">Figure 8</xref>E and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g008">8</xref>F), in some mutant cells the sex chromatin appeared to be incompletely silenced relative to wild-type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g008">Figure 8</xref>F). We also examined three epigenetic signatures of PMSC: histone H3 dimethylated or trimethylated at lysine-9 (H3-2meK9, H3-3meK9) and spreading of HP1&#x003b2; through the XY body &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b016">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b057">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b058">58</xref>&#x0005d; (S. H. Namekawa, unpublished data). We observed defects in sex chromatin localization of all three markers in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> diplotene cells. Although HP1&#x003b2; localization to the X chromosome centromere initially appeared normal at mid-pachynema, we observed <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant diplotene cells that failed to show spreading of HP1&#x003b2; to the entire XY body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g008">Figure 8</xref>G and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g008">8</xref>H). Similarly, we found <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant diplotene cells lacking accumulation of H3-2meK9 and H3-3meK9 marks onto the sex chromatin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g008">Figure 8</xref>I&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g008">8</xref>L).</p><p>Not all <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant diplotene cells showed abnormal localization of HP1&#x003b2; to the sex chromatin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g008">Figure 8</xref>M). In one experiment, 11/27 mutant cells in diplonema lacked HP1&#x003b2; on the XY body, as compared with 2/22 wild-type cells. We hypothesize that the mutant cells with normal HP1&#x003b2; may be those that can complete meiosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g004">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g005">5</xref>). Some of the mutant diplotene cells showing abnormal sex chromatin also had abnormal autosomal &#x003b3;H2AX staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g008">Figure 8</xref>L). &#x003b3;H2AX localizes to double-strand DNA breaks, so this staining may indicate that some diplotene mutant cells are approaching or entering apoptosis &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b059">59</xref>&#x0005d;. We did not observe sex chromatin defects prior to diplonema, but we cannot exclude the possibility that earlier defects exist and the affected cells are rapidly eliminated.</p><p>In the preceding experiments, we staged cells based on XY body internalization. Because this process could be abnormal in the mutant cells, we also staged mutant cells by chromosome morphology using an antibody to SYCP3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g009">Figure 9</xref>). This independently identified <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant diplotene cells lacking HP1&#x003b2; accumulation in the XY body, such as the example in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g009">Figure 9</xref>B. From these results, we conclude that <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant cells establish a normal XY body in mid-pachynema, but then have multiple epigenetic defects in the sex chromatin transition from pachynema to diplonema.</p><fig id="pgen-0030062-g009" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>Abnormal Sex Chromatin in Cells Staged by Chromosome Pairing Status</title><p>(A) Spread of wild-type germ cell stained with DAPI, anti-SYCP3, and anti-HP1&#x003b2; showing chromosome morphology typical of diplonema and internalized XY body with HP1&#x003b2; accumulation.</p><p>(B) Spread of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant germ cell showing normal diplotene chromosome morphology and internalized XY body, but no HP1&#x003b2; accumulation in the XY body.</p><p>XY chromosome pairs are indicated by arrow.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030062.g009"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we find that the DM domain protein DMRT7 is required for male germ cells to complete meiotic prophase but is dispensable in the female germ line. In males, DMRT7 expression is highest in pachytene spermatocytes, and the protein preferentially localizes to the XY body. Consistent with this expression, we found that most mutant male germ cells arrest in pachynema and undergo apoptosis, although a small proportion can progress to diplonema and sometimes beyond. Examination of chromatin and nascent transcription in mutant cells that progressed to diplonema revealed sex chromatin abnormalities, as discussed below.</p><p>The pachytene stage of prophase involves tremendous chromosomal changes as the homologs align, synapse, and recombine. During this period, at least one pachytene surveillance system exists to monitor key events of meiotic progression. Cells in which any of these events is anomalous are efficiently eliminated by apoptosis &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b046">46</xref>&#x0005d;. Another key event of pachynema in male mammals is the packaging of the sex chromosomes into the XY body and the establishment of MSCI. Examination of male meiosis in XYY mice and mice carrying a sex-chromosome-to-autosome translocation showed that cells in which a sex chromosome escapes MSCI are eliminated prior to late-pachynema &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b017">17</xref>&#x0005d;. This indicates that the establishment of MSCI also is subject to surveillance.</p><p>Since the arrest and apoptosis of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant spermatocytes could result from perturbation of any of the critical pachytene events mentioned above, we tested whether they occur abnormally in the mutant cells. We found that chromosomal synapsis and recombination appear normal in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant cells. We therefore focused on the XY body, the most prominent site of DMRT7 accumulation. First, we tested whether the XY body forms and MSCI is established in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant cells. Surprisingly, we found that these cells form an XY body with normal morphology and proper accumulation of all the chromatin marks we examined. Moreover, Cot-1 hybridization and analysis of RBMY expression demonstrated that MSCI initiates normally in the XY body of mid-pachytene <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant cells.</p><p>We did, however, observe three specific defects in the sex chromatin of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant germ cells that avoided arrest in pachynema and were able to enter diplonema. Normally cells accumulate H3-2meK9 and H3-3meK9 marks and HP1&#x003b2; protein on the sex chromatin as they progress to diplonema, but we observed mutant diplotene cells lacking these features. Thus, although a minority of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant germ cells can progress from pachynema to diplonema, there are defects in sex chromatin modification during the transition. A function in male sex chromatin can reconcile the findings that DMRT7 is required for meiosis, but only in males, and is present only in mammals. A proportion of mutant diplotene cells have apparently normal sex chromatin (for example, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g008">Figure 8</xref>M); these are likely to be the cells that can progress beyond diplonema.</p><p>Because most <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant germ cells are eliminated by apoptosis around the time at which we observed sex chromatin defects, a simple model is that the apoptosis is a consequence of the sex chromatin defects. The reciprocal situation (sex chromatin defects caused by apoptosis) is possible, but seems unlikely, because we observed mutant cells with sex chromatin defects but no indications of apoptosis. Alternatively, apoptosis and abnormal sex chromatin may be two independent consequences of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> loss. This question cannot be answered definitively until we know the detailed molecular mechanism of DMRT7.</p><p>A number of other proteins have been identified that interact with the XY body, including histone variants and modified histones, a testis-specific histone methyl transferase, chromobox proteins, an orphan receptor germ-cell nuclear factor, and recombination-related proteins &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b060">60</xref>&#x0005d;. A common feature of these proteins is involvement with heterochromatin and/or transcriptional repression. DMRT7 is unusual among XY body proteins in being related to highly site-specific transcriptional regulators. An attractive speculation is that DMRT7 may provide sequence specificity in recruiting other proteins, such as chromatin modifiers, to the XY body as part of the transition to PMSC. Chromatin regulation may be a common mechanism for DM domain proteins, as we find that other DM domain proteins associate with chromatin modifying complexes (M. W. Murphy, D. Zarkower, and V. J. Bardwell, unpublished data).</p><p>The finding that <italic>Dmrt7</italic> is essential for mammalian meiosis expands the known functions of this gene family. Invertebrate DM domain genes so far have only been found to function in somatic cells. Two other DM domain genes, <italic>Dmrt1</italic> and <italic>Dmrt4,</italic> do affect germ cell development in the mouse. <italic>Dmrt1</italic> is required in pre-meiotic male germ cells for differentiation of gonocytes into spermatogonia, as well as in Sertoli cells, but it is not expressed in meiotic cells &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b031">31</xref>&#x0005d; (S. Kim and D. Zarkower, unpublished data). The requirement for DMRT1 in pre-meiotic germ cells and DMRT7 in meiotic germ cells demonstrates that DM domain proteins act at multiple critical points of male germ cell development. Ovaries of <italic>Dmrt4</italic> mutant females have polyovular follicles (follicles containing multiple oocytes), but it is unknown whether this reflects a defect in the germ line or the soma. It is notable that at least three mammalian DM domain genes affect gonadal development only in one sex, given the similar roles of related proteins in directing sex-specific somatic development in other phyla.</p><p>Strikingly, <italic>Dmrt7</italic> is present, not only in placental mammals, but also in marsupials and a monotreme (egg-laying mammal), the platypus, which has a clear <italic>Dmrt7</italic> ortholog &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b036">36</xref>&#x0005d;. However, no close <italic>Dmrt7</italic> ortholog has been reported in nonmammalian vertebrates, and our database searches did not reveal one. Thus, <italic>Dmrt7</italic> likely arose, presumably by duplication and divergence of another <italic>Dmrt</italic> gene, shortly before or coincident with the mammalian radiation. Monotremes have five X and five Y chromosomes, which form an extended pairing chain during meiosis and appear unrelated to the sex chromosomes of the other mammals &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b061">61</xref>&#x0005d;. The presence of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> in both lineages may support a common origin for either the sex chromosomes or the sex chromatin of monotremes and other mammals. A plausible model is that <italic>Dmrt7</italic> evolved during the establishment of mammalian sex determination to help cope with ancestral differences in gene dosage, chromosome pairing, recombination, or other meiotic issues arising from sex chromosome heteromorphy. In this regard, we speculate that the recruitment of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> during mammalian evolution may be analogous to the recruitment of chromatin regulatory complexes to achieve somatic dosage compensation during evolution of heteromorphic sex chromosomes in several phyla (reviewed in &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b062">62</xref>&#x0005d;). It will be of interest to determine whether DMRT7 localizes to sex chromosomes during monotreme meiosis.</p><p>In summary, we have found that the mammal-specific DM domain protein DMRT7 is essential for meiotic prophase progression in males. DMRT7 localizes to the sex chromosomes after they are assembled into specialized heterochromatin, and many <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant cells have epigenetic defects in the modification of the sex chromatin between pachytene and diplotene. Although <italic>Dmrt7</italic> belongs to an ancient and conserved gene family, it is found only in mammals, and to our knowledge DMRT7 is the only example of a mammal-specific protein that is essential for meiosis. It will be important to determine the precise mechanism by which DMRT7 affects sex chromatin regulation during male meiosis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Generation of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mice.</title><p>A mouse <italic>Dmrt7</italic> cDNA fragment containing sequences from exon 8 was used to screen a mouse BAC library from the 129/SvJ strain (Stratagene, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.stratagene.com">http://www.stratagene.com</ext-link>), and clones containing promoter sequences were isolated and sequenced to obtain <italic>Dmrt7</italic> genomic sequence. The targeting vector pDZ169 (diagrammed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030062-sg002">Figure S2</xref>) was constructed by the following scheme: The vector pDZ157 was used as a backbone vector &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b031">31</xref>&#x0005d;. 3&#x02032; to <italic>Pgk-neo</italic> and the <italic>loxP</italic> site, we inserted, as a XmaI/XmaI DNA fragment, the third intron of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> (from 366 bp to 2,773 bp downstream of exon 3) generated by PCR. 5&#x02032; to <italic>Pgk-neo,</italic> we inserted an EcoRI/NotI PCR fragment extending from 4,107 bp to 336 bp 5&#x02032; of the <italic>Dmrt7</italic> translational start. Finally, we inserted a <italic>loxP</italic> site and NotI site 336 bp 5&#x02032; of the <italic>Dmrt7</italic> translational start. In the resulting vector, the second and third exons of <italic>Dmrt7</italic> are flanked by <italic>loxP</italic> sites (floxed). The <italic>Dmrt7-</italic>containing portions of pDZ169 were completely sequenced.</p><p>pDZ169 was linearized with PmeI and electroporated into CJ7 ES cells (originally derived from the 129S1 strain). Three homologous recombinants were identified from 296 G418-resistant colonies by Southern hybridization by use of a DNA probe from the sequences upstream of exon 1 to screen genomic DNA digested with EcoRI. Homologous recombination was confirmed on both ends of the targeted region by Southern hybridization. Probes for Southern hybridization were made by PCR using primers DM5S10/DM5S11 (5&#x02032; probe) and DM5PR1/DM5PR2 (3&#x02032; probe), listed below. Two targeted ES cell clones containing the floxed allele <italic>Dmrt7<sup>neo</sup></italic> were injected into C57Bl/6 blastocysts to generate chimeras. Chimeric males were bred with C57Bl/6 females to generate heterozygotes carrying <italic>Dmrt7<sup>neo</sup>. Dmrt7<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>/Dmrt7<sup>neo</sup></italic> females were bred with male &#x003b2;<italic>-actin-Cre</italic> transgenic mice to delete the floxed sequences and generate heterozygous <italic>Dmrt7<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic><sup>/&#x0002b;</sup> deletion mutants, which were interbred to generate homozygous <italic>Dmrt7<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mutants.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Genotyping and RT-PCR.</title><p>For genotyping, tail-clip DNA was amplified for 35 cycles. Chromosomal sex was determined by PCR with primers to the Y chromosome gene <italic>Zfy</italic> (below). The wild-type <italic>Dmrt7</italic> allele <italic>Dmrt7<sup>&#x0002b;</sup></italic> was detected by PCR with DM5S4/DM5S5, with an annealing temperature of 60 &#x000b0;C. The <italic>Dmrt7<sup>flox</sup></italic> allele was detected by PCR with DM5S5F/DM7KO7R with an annealing temperature of 62 &#x000b0;C. The deleted <italic>Dmrt7</italic> allele <italic>Dmrt7<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic> was detected with DM5S3/DM7KO7R with an annealing temperature of 62 &#x000b0;C. RT-PCR for <italic>Dmrt7</italic> expression analysis was as described &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b023">23</xref>&#x0005d; using primers SK111/SK112 with an annealing temperature of 62 &#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Primers.</title><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>DM5S3: 5&#x02032;-AGAGTGGATTGAATCGGATAGCTC-3&#x02032;</p></list-item><list-item><p>DM5S4: 5&#x02032;-AGGATCTTAGTGTCGAATGAATAC-3&#x02032;</p></list-item><list-item><p>DM5S5: 5&#x02032;-CCCTTATCCTCCTGCATCCAGATC-3&#x02032;</p></list-item><list-item><p>DM5S10: 5&#x02032;-CAGGCTATGGTTAGACTTGAGCAC-3&#x02032;</p></list-item><list-item><p>DM5S11: 5&#x02032;-CATCACTCGCGGACAAAGATGCAG-3&#x02032;</p></list-item><list-item><p>DM5PR1: 5&#x02032;-CTTCTGCTACAGCCACAGGTCTGG-3&#x02032;</p></list-item><list-item><p>DM5PR2: 5&#x02032;-GAATTCAACTAGTATCTGTCCC-3&#x02032;</p></list-item><list-item><p>DM7KO7R: 5&#x02032;-CGAGGATCAAGCTCAGGTCACTAGG-3&#x02032;</p></list-item><list-item><p>DM5S5F: 5&#x02032;-GATCTGGATGCAGGAGGATAAGGG-3&#x02032;</p></list-item><list-item><p>ZFYF: 5&#x02032;-CCTATTGCATGGACAGCAGTCTTATG-3&#x02032;</p></list-item><list-item><p>ZFYR: 5&#x02032;-GACTAGACATGTTCTTAACATCTGTCC-3&#x02032;</p></list-item><list-item><p>SK111: 5&#x02032;-CCCTTCTGGAAAAGAGAACATAGC-3&#x02032;</p></list-item><list-item><p>SK112: 5&#x02032;-GCTCCAGGGGCCTGTGGCTGTAGC-3&#x02032;</p></list-item><list-item><p>&#x003b2;-<italic>actin</italic>F: 5&#x02032;-TGCGTGACATCAAAGAGAAG-3&#x02032;</p></list-item><list-item><p>&#x003b2;-<italic>actin</italic>R: 5&#x02032;-GATGCCACAGGATTCCATA-3&#x02032;</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Histological analysis and TUNEL assay.</title><p>Dissected testes were fixed in Bouin's fixative or phosphate-buffered formalin overnight at 4 &#x000b0;C, progressively dehydrated in a graded ethanol series, and embedded in paraffin wax. Sections (6 &#x003bc;m) were deparaffinized, rehydrated, and stained with hematoxylin and eosin. For TUNEL analyses, deparaffinized sections were treated with proteinase K for 15 min and quenched in 3.0&#x00025; hydrogen peroxide in PBS for 5 min at room temperature. Subsequently, nuclear staining in apoptotic cells was detected using ApopTag kit (Chemicon, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.chemicon.com">http://www.chemicon.com</ext-link>) according to the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Tissue immunofluorescent staining.</title><p>Slides with paraffin sections were washed in PBT (0.1&#x00025; Tween 20 in PBS) and autoclaved in 10 mM citric acid (pH 6.0) to retrieve antigenicity. Slides were blocked in 5&#x00025; serum (matched to the species of the secondary antibody) in PBS for 1 h at room temperature and incubated with primary antibodies overnight at 4 &#x000b0;C prior to detection with secondary antibodies.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Antibodies.</title><p>Rabbit polyclonal antibodies to DMRT7 were raised against a purified fusion protein containing glutathione-S-transferase (GST) fused to the C-terminal 279 amino acids of DMRT7. Antibodies to GST were removed by GST-affigel 10 chromatography and the antiserum was then purified by GST-DMRT7-affigel 15 chromatography. DMRT7 antibody was used at 1:200 dilution with a goat anti-rabbit secondary antibody (Molecular Probes, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.invitrogen.com">http://www.invitrogen.com</ext-link>) at 1:200 dilution. Other primary antibodies used for immunofluorescence were rat anti-GATA1 (1:200, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scbt.com">http://www.scbt.com</ext-link>, sc-265), goat anti-GATA4 (1:200, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, sc-1237), rat anti-TRA98 (1:200, gift of H. Tanaka and Y. Nishimune), rat anti-BC7 (1:50, gift of H. Tanaka and Y. Nishimune), rat anti-TRA369 (1:200, gift of H. Tanaka and Y. Nishimune), rabbit anti-RAD51 (1:600 Calbiochem, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.calbiochem.com">http://www.calbiochem.com</ext-link>, PC130), mouse anti-GMP-1/SUMO-1 (1:200, Zymed, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://invitrogen.com">http://invitrogen.com</ext-link>, 33&#x02013;2400), rabbit anti-phospho-H2AX (Ser139) (1:200, Upstate, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.millipore.com">http://www.millipore.com</ext-link>, 01&#x02013;164), mouse anti-phospho-H2AX (1:200, Upstate, 05&#x02013;636), mouse anti-SYCP3 (1:200, Abcam, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.abcam.com">http://www.abcam.com</ext-link>, ab12452), rabbit anti-HP1&#x003b2; (1:100, Abcam, ab10478), rabbit anti-H3-2meK9 (1:100, Upstate, 07&#x02013;441), rabbit anti-H3-3meK9 (1:200, Upstate, 07&#x02013;442), rabbit anti-AR (N-20) (1:200, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, sc-816), and mouse anti-&#x003b1;SMA clone 1A4 (1:800, Sigma, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sigmaaldrich.com">http://www.sigmaaldrich.com</ext-link>, A2547). Secondary antibodies used were goat anti-rabbit Alexa 488, goat anti-rabbit Alexa 594, goat anti-rat Alexa 594, and goat anti-mouse Alexa 488 (Molecular Probes) used at 1:250. Donkey anti-goat FITC (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jacksonimmuno.com">http://www.jacksonimmuno.com</ext-link>) and donkey anti-rabbit Texas Red (Jackson) were used at 1:50 according to the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>Meiotic chromosome spread preparations and FISH.</title><p>Meiotic chromosome spread preparations were made from 3-wk-old mice, prepared as described by Reinholdt et al. &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b063">63</xref>&#x0005d;. For analysis of PMSC and Cot-1 RNA FISH, meiotic slides were prepared as previously described &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b016">16</xref>&#x0005d;. Slides containing chromosome spreads or meiotic spermatocytes were subjected to immunofluorescent staining or RNA FISH, as previously described &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b016">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030062-b063">63</xref>&#x0005d;. For combined RNA FISH/immunostaining, we carried out RNA FISH first, followed by immunofluorescence. DNA FISH was performed using chromosome painting (Cambio, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cambio.co.uk">http://www.cambio.co.uk</ext-link>). Z-sections were captured by Zeiss Axioplan microscope (Zeiss, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.zeiss.com">http://www.zeiss.com</ext-link>) and processed by Openlab (Improvision, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.improvision.com">http://www.improvision.com</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen-0030062-sg001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><title>Wild-Type and <italic>Dmrt7</italic> Mutant Meiotic Spreads</title><p>Arrows indicate the location of XY body. SYCP3 antibody staining (green) shows normal synapsis of homologous chromosome synapse in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant cell. DMRT7 protein (red) is localized to the XY body in wild-type (top row) and is not detected in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant (bottom row).</p><p>(726 KB JPG)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.0030062.sg001.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen-0030062-sg002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><title>Targeted Disruption of <italic>Dmrt7</italic></title><p>(A) Diagram of targeting strategy. Homologous recombination of the targeting vector with the wild-type <italic>Dmrt7</italic> allele (<italic>Dmrt7<sup>&#x0002b;</sup></italic>) resulted in the targeted allele <italic>Dmrt<sup>neo</sup>.</italic> This allele contains <italic>loxP</italic> sites flanking the translational start and the second and third exons (containing the DM domain, gray), as well as a neomycine-resistance cassette flanked by Flp recombinase recognition sites (<italic>frt</italic> sites). Mice heterozygous for the <italic>Dmrt1<sup>neo</sup></italic> allele were mated with transgenic mice expressing Cre recombinase, resulting in deletion of the sequence between the two <italic>loxP</italic> sites, including the neo cassette. The resulting deletion allele is called <italic>Dmrt7<sup>&#x02212;</sup>.</italic> Mating of <italic>Dmrt7<sup>neo</sup></italic> mice with transgenic mice expressing the Flpe recombinase excised the neo cassette, generating the <italic>Dmrt7<sup>flox</sup></italic> allele.</p><p>(B) Southern blots of targeted and wild-type ES cell clones. Genomic DNAs from ES cell clones were digested with NsiI/NotI and EcoRI. The 5&#x02032; external probe hybridizes to 14.2-kb (wild-type) and 6-kb (targeted) NsiI/NotI fragments. The 3&#x02032; probe hybridizes to 14.6-kb (wild-type) and 4.7-kb (targeted) EcoRI fragments.</p><p>(C) Testis sections from adult mice. SUMO-1 (green) on XY body is detected in both wild-type (top) and <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant (bottom) section. DMRT7 is detected in wild-type but not detected in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant in SUMO-1-positive cells. (Wild-type images are the same as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030062-g001">Figure 1</xref>D.)</p><p>(3.4 MB JPG)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.0030062.sg002.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen-0030062-sg003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><title>Normal Androgen Receptor Expression in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> Mutant Sertoli Cells</title><p>Testis sections from adult mice stained with antibody to androgen receptor (red) and counterstained with DAPI (blue). In both wild-type (top) and mutant (bottom) testis sections, androgen receptor protein is expressed in Sertoli cell and peritubular myoid cell. Mutant testis section shows abnormal localization of Sertoli cell nuclei, which are displaced from basement membrane.</p><p>AR, androgen receptor.</p><p>(2.3 MB JPG)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.0030062.sg003.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen-0030062-sg004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><title>Ub-H2A Localization to XY Body in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> Mutant Spermatocyte</title><p>Spread pachytene spermatocytes from wild-type (top) and <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant (bottom) mice, stained with antibody to Ub-H2A (green) and DAPI (blue). Arrows indicate XY body. Both wild-type and mutant pachytene cells have Ub-H2A properly localized to XY body.</p><p>(722 KB JPG)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.0030062.sg004.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen-0030062-sg005"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><title>RBMY Silencing in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> Mutant Spermatocytes</title><p>(A) SYCP3 (green) and RBMY (red) immunostaining of spread wild-type and <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant testicular cells. In wild-type and mutant cells, RBMY is expressed at low levels in leptotene stage. In pachytene spermatocytes, RBMY has fallen to background levels in both wild-type and mutant.</p><p>(B) SUMO-1 (green) and RBMY (red) immunostaining of adult testis sections from wild-type and <italic>Dmrt7</italic> mutant. Pre-meiotic cells near the basal membrane express high level of RBMY whereas SUMO-1-positive pachytene cells do not express RBMY, in both wild-type and mutant, indicating proper silencing.</p><p>(5.4 MB JPG)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.0030062.sg005.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank members of the Zarkower and Bardwell labs for many helpful discussions; Dan Camerini-Otero, John Logsdon, and Scott Hawley for insights into evolution of meiotic regulators; Hiromitsu Tanaka, Yoshitake Nishimune, and David Elliot for generously sharing antibodies; and Dies Meijer for sharing <italic>Dhh-Cre</italic> mice. We thank the University of Minnesota Mouse Genetics Laboratory for ES cell injection. Some images were obtained using the Middlebury Biology Imaging Facility, equipped in part through the National Science Foundation (Course, Curriculum, and Laboratory Improvement, 0088412). SHN is a research fellow of the Japan Society for Promotion of Science.</p></ack><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>DM</term><def><p>Doublesex/MAB-3 domain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ES</term><def><p>embryonic stem</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FISH</term><def><p>fluorescence in situ hybridization</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GST</term><def><p>glutathione-S-transferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HP1&#x003b2;</term><def><p>heterochromatin protein 1 beta</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>&#x003b3;H2AX</term><def><p>phosphorylated H2AX</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MSCI</term><def><p>meiotic sex chromosome inactivation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>P14</term><def><p>postnatal day 14</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PMSC</term><def><p>postmeiotic sex chromatin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RT-PCR</term><def><p>reverse transcriptase-PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SUMO-1</term><def><p>small ubiquitin-related modifier 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Ub-H2A</term><def><p>ubiquitinated H2A</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pgen-0030062-b001"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morelli</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Not all germ cells are created equal: Aspects of sexual dimorphism in mammalian meiosis</article-title><source>Reproduction</source><volume>130</volume><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16322537</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b002"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Handel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Eppig</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Sexual dimorphism in the regulation of mammalian meiosis</article-title><source>Curr Top Dev Biol</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9352191</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b003"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hassold</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>To err (meiotically) is human: The genesis of human aneuploidy</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11283700</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b004"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Genetic analysis of chromosome pairing, recombination, and cell cycle control during first meiotic prophase in mammals</article-title><source>Endocr Rev</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16543383</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b005"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Disteche</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Dosage compensation in mammals: Fine-tuning the expression of the X chromosome</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>1848</fpage><lpage>1867</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16847345</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b006"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huynh</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>X-chromosome inactivation: A hypothesis linking ontogeny and phylogeny</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>410</fpage><lpage>418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15818384</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b007"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Handel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Sex chromosomes, recombination, and chromatin conformation</article-title><source>Chromosoma</source><volume>102</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8432196</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b008"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahadevaiah</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baudat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogakou</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Recombinational DNA double-strand breaks in mice precede synapsis</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11242108</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b009"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jablonka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1988</year><article-title>Meiotic pairing constraints and the activity of sex chromosomes</article-title><source>J Theor Biol</source><volume>133</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3226141</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b010"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Odorisio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgoyne</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>The meiotic checkpoint monitoring synapsis eliminates spermatocytes via p53-independent apoptosis</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9500548</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b011"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoyer-Fender</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Molecular aspects of XY body formation</article-title><source>Cytogenet Genome Res</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15051945</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b012"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandez-Capetillo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahadevaiah</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Celeste</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Romanienko</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Camerini-Otero</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>H2AX is required for chromatin remodeling and inactivation of sex chromosomes in male mouse meiosis</article-title><source>Dev Cell</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12689589</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b013"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baarends</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoogerbrugge</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Roest</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ooms</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vreeburg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Histone ubiquitination and chromatin remodeling in mouse spermatogenesis</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><volume>207</volume><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10068466</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b014"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Aprelikova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>BRCA1, histone H2AX phosphorylation, and male meiotic sex chromosome inactivation</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>2135</fpage><lpage>2142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15589157</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b015"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Heijden</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Derijck</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Posfai</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Giele</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelczar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Chromosome-wide nucleosome replacement and H3.3 incorporation during mammalian meiotic sex chromosome inactivation</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17237782</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b016"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Namekawa</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarrey</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Postmeiotic sex chromatin in the male germline of mice</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>660</fpage><lpage>667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16581510</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b017"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahadevaiah</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgoyne</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Pachytene asynapsis drives meiotic sex chromosome inactivation and leads to substantial postmeiotic repression in spermatids</article-title><source>Dev Cell</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16580996</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamu</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Evidence for evolutionary conservation of sex-determining genes</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>391</volume><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9490411</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b019"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erdman</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Burtis</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>The <italic>Drosophila</italic> doublesex proteins share a novel zinc finger related DNA-binding domain</article-title><source>Embo J</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8440242</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b020"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zarkower</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Establishing sexual dimorphism: Conservation amidst diversity?</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11256069</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b021"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgkin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1988</year><article-title><italic>mab-3,</italic> a gene required for sex-specific yolk protein expression and a male-specific lineage in <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content></article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>1019</fpage><lpage>1031</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3046751</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b022"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ridge</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1980</year><article-title>Sex and the single cell. I. On the action of major loci affecting sex determination in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content></article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>94</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6771185</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b023"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kettlewell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardwell</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarkower</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Sexually dimorphic expression of multiple doublesex-related genes in the embryonic mouse gonad</article-title><source>Gene Expr Patterns</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12609607</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b024"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volff</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarkower</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardwell</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schartl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Evolutionary dynamics of the DM domain gene family in metazoans</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><volume>57</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>S241</fpage><lpage>S249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15008421</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b025"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornung</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Asakawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>A duplicated copy of DMRT1 in the sex-determining region of the Y chromosome of the medaka, <named-content content-type="genus-species">Oryzias latipes</named-content></article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>99</volume><fpage>11778</fpage><lpage>11783</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12193652</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b026"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>McClive</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Western</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Conservation of a sex-determining gene</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>402</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10604464</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b027"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kettlewell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarkower</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Temperature-dependent expression of turtle <italic>Dmrt1</italic> prior to sexual differentiation</article-title><source>Genesis</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10705377</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b028"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kettlewell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardwell</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarkower</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Expression of <italic>Dmrt1</italic> in the genital ridge of mouse and chicken embryos suggests a role in vertebrate sexual development</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><volume>215</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10545231</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b029"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagahama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinomiya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>DMY is a Y-specific DM-domain gene required for male development in the medaka fish</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>417</volume><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12037570</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b030"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Kettlewell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>A region of human Chromosome 9p required for testis development contains two genes related to known sexual regulators</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>996</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10332030</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b031"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Sullivan</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardwell</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarkower</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title><italic>Dmrt1,</italic> a gene related to worm and fly sexual regulators, is required for mammalian testis differentiation</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>2587</fpage><lpage>2595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11040213</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b032"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balciuniene</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardwell</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarkower</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Mice mutant in the DM domain gene <italic>dmrt4</italic> are viable and fertile but have polyovular follicles</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>8984</fpage><lpage>8991</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16982677</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b033"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saude</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lourenco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmeirim</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title><italic>terra</italic> is a left-right asymmetry gene required for left-right synchronization of the segmentation clock</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>918</fpage><lpage>920</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16136187</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b034"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokubo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kettlewell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarkower</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Targeted disruption of the DM domain containing transcription factor Dmrt2 reveals an essential role in somite patterning</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><volume>290</volume><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16387292</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b035"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>A <italic>Drosophila</italic> doublesex-related gene, <italic>terra,</italic> is involved in somitogenesis in vertebrates</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>126</volume><fpage>1259</fpage><lpage>1268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10021344</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b036"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veith</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Klattig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dettai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Englert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Male-biased expression of X-chromosomal DM domain-less <italic>Dmrt8</italic> genes in the mouse</article-title><source>Genomics</source><volume>88</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16488114</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b037"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellve</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavicchia</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Millette</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatnagar</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1977</year><article-title>Spermatogenic cells of the prepuberal mouse. Isolation and morphological characterization</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">874003</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b038"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yomogida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohtani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Harigae</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimune</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Developmental stage- and spermatogenic cycle-specific expression of transcription factor GATA-1 in mouse Sertoli cells</article-title><source>Development</source><volume>120</volume><fpage>1759</fpage><lpage>1766</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7924983</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b039"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Inselman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Handel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Matunis</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>SUMO modified proteins localize to the XY body of pachytene spermatocytes</article-title><source>Chromosoma</source><volume>113</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15349788</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b040"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vigodner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Testicular expression of small ubiquitin-related modifier-1 (SUMO-1) supports multiple roles in spermatogenesis: Silencing of sex chromosomes in spermatocytes, spermatid microtubule nucleation, and nuclear reshaping</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><volume>282</volume><fpage>480</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15950612</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b041"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lints</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Emmons</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Regulation of sex-specific differentiation and mating behavior in <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content> by a new member of the DM domain transcription factor family</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>2390</fpage><lpage>2402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12231628</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b042"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawamata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Mice deficient in <italic>Dmrt7</italic> show infertility with spermatogenic arrest at pachytene stage</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>580</volume><fpage>6442</fpage><lpage>6446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17098235</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b043"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nozaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuchida</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>A germ cell-specific nuclear antigen recognized by a monoclonal antibody raised against mouse testicular germ cells</article-title><source>Int J Androl</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9568529</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b044"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koshimizu</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimune</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>A novel stage-specific differentiation antigen is expressed on mouse testicular germ cells during early meiotic prophase</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><volume>49</volume><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8286583</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b045"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Koshimizu</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimune</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Characterization of male meiotic germ cell-specific antigen (Meg 1) by monoclonal antibody TRA 369 in mice</article-title><source>Mol Reprod Dev</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1449797</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b046"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roeder</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailis</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>The pachytene checkpoint</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10973068</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b047"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heyting</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Moens</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>van Raamsdonk</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vink</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1987</year><article-title>Identification of two major components of the lateral elements of synaptonemal complexes of the rat</article-title><source>Eur J Cell Biol</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3552678</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b048"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lammers</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Offenberg</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>van Aalderen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vink</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>The gene encoding a major component of the lateral elements of synaptonemal complexes of the rat is related to X-linked lymphocyte-regulated genes</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>1137</fpage><lpage>1146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8289794</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b049"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plug</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Keegan</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoekstra</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Changes in protein composition of meiotic nodules during mammalian meiosis</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9443891</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b050"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mruk</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Sertoli-Sertoli and Sertoli-germ cell interactions and their significance in germ cell movement in the seminiferous epithelium during spermatogenesis</article-title><source>Endocr Rev</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>747</fpage><lpage>806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15466940</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b051"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindeboom</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillemans</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Karis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaegle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>A tissue-specific knockout reveals that Gata1 is not essential for Sertoli cell function in the mouse</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>5405</fpage><lpage>5412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12954777</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b052"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bitgood</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Sertoli cell signaling by Desert hedgehog regulates the male germline</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8805249</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b053"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solari</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1974</year><article-title>The behavior of the XY pair in mammals</article-title><source>Int Rev Cytol</source><volume>38</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4854664</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b054"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahadevaiah</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Odorisio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattigan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Szot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Mouse homologs of the human AZF candidate gene RBM are expressed in spermatogonia and spermatids and map to a Y chromosome deletion interval associated with a high incidence of sperm abnormalities</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9499427</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b055"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grigoriev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahadevaiah</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ojarikre</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Toure</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Does <italic>Rbmy</italic> have a role in sperm development in mice?</article-title><source>Cytogenet Genome Res</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>330</fpage><lpage>336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15051956</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b056"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgoyne</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>M31 and macroH2A1.2 colocalize at the pseudoautosomal region during mouse meiosis</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><volume>114</volume><fpage>3367</fpage><lpage>3375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11591824</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b057"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greaves</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rangasamy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Devoy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall Graves</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tremethick</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>The X and Y chromosomes assemble into H2A.Z-containing &#x0005b;corrected&#x0005d; facultative heterochromatin &#x0005b;corrected&#x0005d; following meiosis</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>5394</fpage><lpage>5405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16809775</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b058"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyar</surname><given-names>FZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Dynamic histone modifications mark sex chromosome inactivation and reactivation during mammalian spermatogenesis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>16583</fpage><lpage>16587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15536132</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b059"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rogakou</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilch</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonner</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>DNA double-stranded breaks induce histone H2AX phosphorylation on serine 139</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>273</volume><fpage>5858</fpage><lpage>5868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9488723</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b060"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Handel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>The XY body: A specialized meiotic chromatin domain</article-title><source>Exp Cell Res</source><volume>296</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15120994</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b061"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grutzner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rens</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsend-Ayush</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Mogharbel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>In the platypus, a meiotic chain of ten sex chromosomes shares genes with the bird Z and mammal X chromosomes</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>432</volume><fpage>913</fpage><lpage>917</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15502814</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b062"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegal</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>The evolution of dosage-compensation mechanisms</article-title><source>Bioessays</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>1106</fpage><lpage>1114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11084626</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b063"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinholdt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schimenti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Forward genetic screens for meiotic and mitotic recombination-defective mutants in mice</article-title><source>Methods Mol Biol</source><volume>262</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14769957</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b064"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaeth</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Creemers</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hack</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>de Rooij</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Correlation of meiotic events in testis sections and microspreads of mouse spermatocytes relative to the mid-pachytene checkpoint</article-title><source>Chromosoma</source><volume>113</volume><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15338235</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030062-b065"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moses</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1980</year><article-title>New cytogenetic studies on mammalian meiosis</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Serio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Martini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><source>Animal models in human reproduction</source><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Raven</publisher-name><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>190</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="ack3" fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing interests.</bold> The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn id="n102" fn-type="previously-at"><p>A previous version of this article appeared as an Early Online Release on March 7, 2007 (doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pgen.0030062.eor">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030062.eor</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn id="ack1" fn-type="con"><p><bold>Author contributions.</bold> All authors conceived and designed the experiments and analyzed the data. SK, SHN, LMN, and JOW performed the experiments. JOW contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools. SK, SHN, JOW, JTL, VJB, and DZ wrote the paper.</p></fn><fn id="ack2" fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by the US National Institutes of Health (GM059152) and the Minnesota Medical Foundation. LMN was supported by the Bicentennial Fund of Middlebury College.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>





